Fran: When you've got a young person whose
family is say, bringing them to sessions
and who referred them to sessions and who
talks to them about their mental health.
It's amazing to see how much difference
that makes, because if I'm working with
someone - I'm working with a young man at
the minute, for instance, who I'm talking
to his mum a couple of times a month as
well, and getting her to go through the
stuff that we go through in sessions with
him, because that's really helping him
to - his problem is that you can't, he
struggles to talk to people, he struggles
to share, he doesn't want to worry people.
So bringing his mum into that and
her being very involved in the work
that we do is helping him to realise,
okay, well, I don't, I can't only
do this when I have my session with
Fran, I can also do it with my mum.
Tamzin: When young people have got good
relationships with parents, carers,
and siblings, you often find that they
actually probably take what we give
them in terms of the therapy tools a
lot better, because they've got those
kind of people to lean on as well.
Fran: As a mental health worker, anywhere
ever in the country at the minute, really
we're limited to how many sessions we can
give to people, so, I think there's a big
difference between knowing that you're
leaveing someone when you're finished
working with them, you're leaving them
with a secure family attachment that can
help them to continue their progress.
Or if you're finishing with someone who
doesn't really have that support network
of a family, that they can sometimes,
you know, you worry that they're not
gonna be able to continue that progress.
'Cause they're going to be
back to the place where they
haven't really got anyone.
Tamzin: When they haven't got that
relationship with their parents.
And pretty much, you know, it's
50/50, with a lot of young people
we work with, these young people
can't talk to their parents.
So you often find them more isolated.
You often find that their
problems are a lot worse.
I've took young people to A&E
because they've not been able
to talk to their mum or dad.
Fran: Sometimes parents you work with
who really want to be supportive and
are struggling with things themselves.
But I think even that, you know, they're
having a hard time, but they want to help
and they want to be there for their kid.
It can just, it can just make, it can
make all the difference really between
a sort of successful recovery and, you
know, somebody who needs to keep coming
back for different types of support.